Guide to the Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part III WAG.025.003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part III
1903-2009
1960-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
WAG.025.003
418 Linear Feet in 394 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 24 card file boxes, 12 oversize flat boxes, and 1 folder in a shared oversize flat box
The Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) is an umbrella group of Jewish trade unions and fraternal organizations. Founded in 1934, the JLC's initial goals were to organize opposition to Nazism and provide assistance to the victims of Nazi persecution. As the immediate need for relief passed, the JLC turned its energies toward various civil, human, and trade union rights causes. Though largely focused on issues of domestic social and economic justice after the 1950s, the JLC continued to campaign on international matters, particularly the support of the State of Israel and the opposition of discrimination against Soviet Jews. Part III of the JLC Records focus primarily on the JLC's post-war activities, though some materials from its relief and rescue period are also present. The records in Part III, which date mostly from the 1960s to the 1990s, reflect the diversity of the JLC's interests and areas of advocacy and the JLC's role as a liaison between the Jewish community and organized labor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The first shipment of the Jewish Labor Committee Records arrived at the Tamiment Library in 1984. The accession numbers associated with these donations are 1984.002 and 1984.006. A number of addition donations to the collection have been made by the JLC and its individual members over the years. The majority of materials that comprise Part III of the collection were likely donated throughout the 2000s, including a donation by Florence Cohen in 2007 and presumably by the JLC as a whole in 2011. Some of the accession numbers associated with the Part III donations include 2008.014 and 2011.131.
Four audiocassette tapes from National Alumni Conferences, a scrapbook of news clippings on Nazism, the materials that comprise Series VIII were found in the repository and added to the collection in May 2014. The accession numbers associated with the audiotapes is 2014.098. The accession number associated with the scrapbook is 2014.136. The accession number associated with Series VIII is 2014.113.
Appraisal
During the processing which occurred in 2013 and 2014, materials that document the JLC's processes and activities were retained, but individual examples of these processes and activities were weeded from the collection. For instance, copies of blank registration forms from the JLC's various conferences and lists of conference attendees were retained, but individual registration forms were not retained. Similarly, information about the JLC's internship program was maintained, but personnel files on interns (which also included Social Security numbers) were designated for disposal. Requests for reimbursement completed by conference attendees and the JLC's local chapters were discarded, but expense reports were retained.
Obvious duplicates within individual folders were sampled and the remainder of the duplicates discarded. Some administrative materials relating to the creation of the JLC's biennial convention journals, mainly pertaining to payment for advertisements in the journals, were also discarded. The archivist also discarded refund requests from individuals who did not ultimately attend the JLC's conferences, some materials relating to conference hotel arrangements, order forms for T-shirts, and individual checks.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Separated Materials
During the processing work that occurred after 1985 through 2012, some materials from the Jewish Labor Committee Records were separated to other Tamiment Library collections. Photographs and other graphic material were separated to the partially processed Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Photographs (PHOTOS 048). Posters, artwork, artifacts, and other ephemera were separated to the unprocessed Jewish Labor Committee Ephemera (EPHEMERA 003) collection.
Also during this period, certain materials were separated to external institutions. A portion of materials from the JLC Records at the Tamiment Library were donated to the Center for Jewish History's American Jewish Historical Society in 1997. Throughout the 1990s, Tamiment donated approximately 300 audio tapes, mostly recordings of the JLC's radio broadcasts or of various JLC events, to the Center for Jewish History's YIVO Institute for Jewish Research. In 2009, Tamiment also donated to YIVO approximately 4 linear feet of Yiddish transcripts of the JLC's radio program, as well as family photographs of Martin Lapan, former Executive Director of the JLC. Eight volumes of Holocaust survivor lists, which were duplicated in the JLC records at Tamiment, were donated to the Museum of Jewish Heritage in 1990.
During the processing work that occurred in 2013 and 2014, significant runs of the JLC's publications and the publications of other organizations collected by the JLC were separated for library cataloging. These publications are accessible via NYU's online catalog, BobCat.
Related Archival Materials
The following Jewish Labor Committee materials are located at this repository:
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Part I (WAG 025.001)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Part II (WAG 025.002)
Jewish Labor Committee, Boston Records (WAG 159)
Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records (WAG 160)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Oral History Collection (OH 027)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Photograph Collection (PHOTOS 048)
Jewish Labor Committee Ephemera (EPHEMERA 003)
Issues of the JLC Review
Issues of JLC Outlook
Issues of the JLC Civil Rights Newsletter
JLC Biennial Convention Journals
The following related archival collections are also located at the Tamiment Library:
Ad Hoc Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties Records (WAG 037)
Julius Bernstein Papers (WAG 116)
Edward S. Goldstein: Jewish Labor Committee Research Files (WAG 232)
Isaiah Minkoff Papers (WAG 086)
Jacob Pat Papers (WAG 127)
Baruch Charney Vladeck Papers (TAM 037)
The records of the National Conference on Soviet Jewry and the National Jewish Community Relations Advisory Council are located at the Center for Jewish History's American Jewish Historical Society in New York City.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into ten series:
Series I: National Administration; Series II: Operations and Subject Files; Series III: Officers and Staff Members; Subseries A: Lasar Epstein; Subseries B: Samuel Estrin; Subseries C: Martin Lapan; Subseries D: Vladka Meed; Subseries E: Benjamin Tabachinsky; Subseries F: Michael Perry; Subseries G: Other Officers and Staff Members; Series IV: Regional Offices and Local Chapters; Series V: Departments, Chapters, and Divisions; Subseries A: Anti-Discrimination Department; Subseries B: National Trade Union Council (NTUC); Subseries C: Women's Division; Subseries D: Yiddish Department; Subseries E: Educators' Chapter; Series VI: Jewish Labour Committee, Canada; Series VII: Microfilm; Series VIII: Tamiment Library Collection of Jewish Labor Committee Records; Series IX: Archived Website; and Series X: Media and Graphics.
Part III of the Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) collection is organized into 8 series, with a number of sub-series, as follows:
Series I: Minutes, 1957-1989; Series II: General Files, 1955-1993; Series III: Field Office Files, 1944-1978; Series IV: Jewish Labor Committee of Canada, 1957-1978; Series V: Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1952-1964; Series VI; Officers' and Staff Files, 1952-1984; Series VII: JLC Relations with Welfare Funds and Local Federations, 1939-1983; and Series VIII: Departments and Divisions of the JLC, 1945-1969.
All series are arranged alphabetically, except for Series V and Series VIII.A, which are arranged chronologically by year and then alphabetically within years.
Scope and Content Note
The Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) Records throughly document the entire history of the organization, from its founding in 1934 up to the 2000s. The records trace the evolution of the JLC from a rescue-and-relief organization during the World War II era to its role as a liaison between the Jewish and labor communities in the latter half of the twentieth century. Though earlier material is present, the majority of the records in Part III of the collection date from the 1960s to the 1990s. Researchers interested in earlier material should also consult Part I (WAG 025.001) and Part II (WAG 025.002) of the collection, located at this repository. The first five series in Part III document the activities of the JLC in the United States, while the last series documents the JLC's Canadian branch.
Approximately one-third of the collection is comprised of the general subject and programming files maintained by various members of the JLC staff, starting in the post-war era as the JLC broadened its agenda. These files reflect the range of the JLC's interests and activities and contain material produced by the JLC and by the many organizations it worked with or researched. Though mostly focused on domestic activities, the materials reflect the overlap between issues at home and abroad. For instance, the JLC was dedicated to combatting discrimination of all forms, actively involved in the civil rights movement in the United States while at the same time working to raise awareness about the oppression of Soviet Jews. The materials reflect the JLC's close relationships with other national labor and Jewish organizations.
The records of the JLC's Anti-Discrimination Department also make up a significant portion of the collection. Spanning from the 1940s to the 1960s, these records detail the JLC's efforts to end discrimination through lobbying and collaboration with various labor, Jewish, and/or civil rights groups. Other divisions represented in the collection illuminate some of the JLC's other areas of prioritization from the 1950s onward, while personal papers of prominent leaders within the JLC reflect the areas of interest for each individual.
To a lesser extent, files related to the administration of the JLC at the national level, including the records of its national conferences, governing bodies, and fundraising efforts, signify what the JLC deemed its greatest accomplishments and what its most pressing needs were moving forward. The records of the JLC's field offices and regional chapters provide insight into how the JLC exerted influence at the local level and reveal the issues of concern to the labor and Jewish communities in specific regions. A small amount of material also documents the now defunct Canadian JLC, a group that often mirrored the U.S. JLC in its goals and activities, particularly regarding anti-discrimination campaigns.
Historical Note
The Jewish Labor Committee (JLC), an umbrella group of Jewish trade unions and fraternal organizations, was founded on February 25, 1934, largely to lobby for the American labor movement's support against the growing threat of Nazism. The JLC's first president, Baruch Charney Vladeck, was active in the Jewish Labor Bund, one of the JLC's founding organizations. Leaders of the Workmen's Circle, the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA), and the Jewish Daily Forward also cofounded the JLC. A Canadian branch of the JLC was formed two years later, with a similar mission as the U.S. JLC.
The JLC's initial goals were to organize opposition to Nazism and provide assistance to the victims of Nazi persecution. By working with European resistance movements, the JLC was able to aid the rescue of several thousand labor and socialist activists and their families. One of the many relief efforts the JLC organized was a child "adoption" program, whereby unions and other organizations and individuals served as "parent" sponsors to children orphaned or otherwise affected by the Holocaust. Sponsors gave the children financial support to be put toward food, clothing, school materials, and other items. The JLC also provided immigration assistance and offered help with employment and housing for refugees who came to the United States.
After World War II, the JLC continued its relief programs for Holocaust victims. As the immediate need for aid started to decline, the JLC shifted much of its attention to supporting the U.S. labor movement and raising awareness about issues of concern to the American Jewish community. In a departure from its earlier anti-Zionist stance, the JLC helped mobilize the labor movement's support for the creation of the State of Israel in 1948. In the decades that followed, the JLC would continue its efforts to garner support for Israel and its trade union principles.
From the 1950s onward, the JLC increasingly focused its energies on encouraging support for the labor movement's issues within the Jewish community, and vice versa. The JLC thus solidified its role as a link between the labor movement and the organized Jewish community in the latter half of the twentieth century. It campaigned on a variety of issues related to civil rights, human rights, and trade union rights. Though mostly concerned with domestic matters, the JLC also continued to be active in foreign affairs.
The JLC's concern with the spread of Nazi propaganda during World War II foretold its involvement in the civil rights movement in the 1950s and 1960s. The National Trade Union Council for Human Rights (NTUC) was founded by the JLC in response to the growth of anti-Semitic and anti-African American groups. Through the efforts of the NTUC and the wider JLC, the JLC combatted discrimination in the workplace, in education, and in society at large by supporting civil rights legislation, working with U.S. and Canadian unions to establish local committees, and participating in civil rights marches and the Leadership Conference for Civil Rights.
The JLC was also one of the earliest advocates for the Jewish population living in the Soviet Union. The organization raised awareness among the labor community about the widespread oppression of the Jewish community under the Communist governments, which limited their right to religious expression even more so than other religious groups. In 1963, the JLC was one of the founding members of the American Jewish Conference on Soviet Jewry (later the National Conference on Soviet Jewry), an organization that would play an important role in the Soviet Jewry movement.
The Canadian branch of the JLC ceased its operations in the 1970s, but the U.S. JLC continued to be active on the home front and internationally. Trade union seminars in Israel, organized by the JLC, educated a new generation of emerging American labor leaders about the development of the State of Israel and its relationship to the U.S. labor movement.
In the 1980s, the JLC took a strong stance on workers' rights, supporting the fights to stop plant closings, increase the minimum wage, and prevent the reintroduction of industrial homework. Holocaust education was also a top priority during this period, with the JLC Educators' Chapter playing a key role in the formation of the Holocaust and Jewish Resistance Teachers' Program. The program, led by JLC vice president Vladka Meed, sent thirty secondary teachers to Israel and Poland in the summer of 1985 to visit memorials and historic sites and receive instruction from local historians and academics. The mid 1980s also saw the JLC heighten its awareness of its relationship to other ethnicities and cultures, as evidenced by the formation of the Ethnic Labor Coalition (ELC). The ELC works to strengthen support for the labor movement in the Italian, African American, Hispanic, and Jewish communities, as well as improve relations between these different ethnic groups.
Internationally, the JLC remained committed to the Soviet Jewry movement, cofounding the Trade Union Council for Soviet Jewry with the AFL-CIO in the late 1980s. The JLC also created the Labor for a Secure Israel program, which mobilizes support for Israel in U.S. states with small Jewish populations. In 1988, the JLC made a presentation before the Office of the United States Trade Representative in defense of Israel against allegations that Palestinian workers were being mistreated.
In addition to its many ongoing programs, the JLC continues to campaign for issues of concern to the labor community. The JLC is a member of the Jewish Council for Public Affairs (formerly the National Jewish Community Relations Advisory Council) and works with the AFL-CIO and other Jewish and labor organizations to further its mission. Recently, the JLC has advocated on behalf of agricultural and sweatshop workers and hosted local Labor Seders. With many local chapters located through the country and an active national leadership, the JLC continues to be an influential presence in both the Jewish and labor communities.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Series VII contains microfilm.
Jews -- United States -- Attitudes toward Israel.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Germany.; Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Jews -- Soviet Union -- Social conditions.; Israel.; Newsletters.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- 20th century.; Minutes (administrative records); Middle East.; Printed ephemera.; New York (N.Y.).; Civil rights -- United States.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Reports.; Canada.; Jewish refugees.; Poland; World War, 1939-1945 -- Jews -- Rescue.; Jews -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Antisemitism.; Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Jewish labor unions.; Jewish-Arab relations; Labor -- Religious aspects -- Judaism.; Card files.; Clippings (information artifacts); Notes.; Speeches.; American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee; Estrin, Samuel; Miller, Lenore; Tabachinsky, Benjamin; Pat, Jacob, 1890-1966; Muravchik, Emanuel; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); National Jewish Community Relations Advisory Council (U.S.); Miedzyrzecki, Feigele Peltel; National Conference on Soviet Jewry (U.S.); Taylor, Betty Kaye, -2011; Jewish Labor Committee (Canada); Bykofsky, Sydney; Histadrut ha-kelalit shel ha-ʻovdim be-Erets-Yiśraʼel; AFL-CIO; Greenberg, Paul; Lapan, Martin, d. 2008; Perry, Michael S.; DiLorenzo, Jeannette; Cohen, Florence R.; Magidson, Herb; Epstein, Lasar; Held, Adolph, 1885-1969; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.). Anti-Discrimination Department; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
- Series I: National Administration, 1934-2008
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains the records related to the administration of the JLC at the national level. The national bodies documented in the form of minutes, agendas, and memoranda, correspondence, and form mailings include the Executive Board/National Executive Board, the National Executive Committee, the Office Committee, the Administrative Committee, and others.
  The JLC's fundraising efforts are documented in the allocations correspondence sent to local Jewish federations, national welfare funds, and other organizations, arranged chronologically, by city and/or region, and by the type of organization being solicited. The series also contains reports and mailings prepared by the JLC to the Large City Budgeting Conference (later the National Funding Councils) of the Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds (renamed the Council of Jewish Federations in 1979) in support of its funding requests. These reports and mailings call out what the JLC perceived as the highlights of its activities during the represented years. Similarly, financial reports and ledgers, many compiled by Arthur Goldberg, document the JLC's expenses and track its attempts to solicit allocations from local welfare funds.
  Records from the JLC biennial conventions reflect the evolution of the JLC's standpoints on various issues. Speeches and biographies of speakers, reports, publicity, lists of delegates, minutes and other material produced by various committees, correspondence, and other documents demonstrate the planning behind the conventions and the events that took place at each meeting. In particular, the resolutions drafted and approved at the conventions provide an apt summary of the issues that the JLC emphasized throughout the twentieth century and document the changes in its priorities. (Additional resolutions may be found in Series II.) There is also a small amount of administrative material related to the creation of the JLC's biennial convention journals. The journals themselves are cataloged separately and are searchable via NYU's online catalog, Bobcat.
  A few files relate to the Atran Center's moves to new headquarters in the late 1970s and the early 1980s. Materials in Box 441 are likely the office files of May "Mazie" Vladeck Bromberg, a member of the JLC staff and daughter of the JLC's founder, Baruch Charney Vladeck.
  Arrangement
  Records of the JLC's governing bodies are listed first, and other materials are listed alphabetically. Materials in Box 441 remain in their original order.
  - Administrative Committee: Minutes, 1957-1988 (Box 118)
  - Administrative Committee, 1947-1949, 1967, 1978, 1987-1995; 2 folder (Box 467)
  - Executive Committee, 1977-1989 (Box 118A, Folder 1-4)
  - Executive Committee, 1978, 1990-2004; 24 folders (Box 467)
  - Executive Committee, 2001-2007; 2 folders (Box 468)
  - Executive Committee: Emergency Meeting, 1940; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Executive Committee: Minutes (Yiddish), 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Executive Committee and Finance Committee, 2002; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Executive Committee and National Board, 2000-2007; 2 folders (Box 468)
  - Executive Staff: Minutes, 1958-1969, 1974-1978 (Box 118A, Folder 5)
  - Interim Committee: Minutes, 1964-1970 (Box 118A, Folder 6-8)
  - Interim Committee, 1967-1970; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Labor Cabinet, 1990-1995, 1999-2000; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - National Board and National Executive Board, 1988-2001; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - National Board, 1994-2001; 7 folders (Box 468)
  - National Board, 1996; 1 folder (Box 470)
  - National Executive Board, 1987-1995; 5 folders (Box 468)
  - National Executive Board, 1990-1995; 4 folders (Box 470)
  - National Executive Committee: Minutes, 1963-1988 (Box 118A, Folder 9-13)
  - Office Committee: Minutes, 1959-1977 (Box 118A, Folder 14-16)
  - Office Committee, 1941-1949; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Office Reports (Yiddish), 1964-1968; 1 folder (Box 468)
  - Other Committees and Committee Meeting Fragments, 1947-1949, 1964, 1968, 1981, undated; 4 folders (Box 468)
  - Planning/Strategic Planning Committee, 1953, 1994-1997; 3 folders (Box 468)
  - Affiliates: Dues/Contributions, 1990, 1998; 1 folder (Box 465)
  - Allocations: Chronological Files, 1985-1998; 17 folders (Box 478)
  - Allocations: General, 1946-1960, 1979-1982 (Box 251, Folder 1-4)
  - Allocations: City Files-- Aberdeen, WA — Benton Harbor, MI, 1941-1979, undated (Box 253)